Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is daf
Ayin דף עין daf Ayin 70, the what is it 27th day
of the Omer עומר. Omer.
And we pick up on the middle of Samech Tet amud bet
ס"ט עמוד ב', Samech Tet amud bet, where it says Kohani Leviei
VeYisraeli כהני לויא וישראלי. Kohani Leviei VeYisraeli. It's two dots, it's about,
I don't even know, about 15 middle middle about 15 lines down
in the wide lines. Line starts with the word Minalan מנלן. Minalan.
Okay, so these are all the different groups that came up with
Ezra עזרא, Ezra, and now what we're going to be doing is
just quoting a lot of Pesukim פסוקים Pesukim from Ezra עזרא, Ezra,
which say most of what the Mishnah משנה Mishnah said. So it
actually Mishnah משנה Mishnah actually is this is a pretty historical record,
I mean, you know, whether everything is explicit in the verses is
a different question, but a lot of it is. So let's take
a look. Minalan Disliku מנלן דסליקו? Minalan Disliku? How do we know
that every members of Kohani Leviei and Yisraeli כהני לויא וישראלי Kohani
Leviei VeYisraeli all came up with Ezra עזרא? Ezra? Dechtiv דכתיב, Dechtiv,
it says Vayeshvu Hakohanim Vehaleviim Umin Haam Vehamshorerim Vehashoarim וישבו הכהנים והלוים
ומן העם והמשררים והשוערים. Vayeshvu Hakohanim Vehaleviim Umin Haam Vehamshorerim Vehashoarim. And
the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim and the Leviim לויים Leviim and from the
bnei am בני עם bnei am and the meshorerim משררים meshorerim and
the shoarim שוערים, shoarim, which is understood to mean the Leviim לויים
Leviim who do the singing or the playing and those that watch
the gates. Vehanetinim Beareihem והנתינים בעריהם Vehanetinim Beareihem and the Netinim נתינים,
Netinim, so that's the Giveonim גבעונים Giveonim and we're going to that's
later in the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, Vechol Yisrael Beareihem וכל ישראל בעריהם.
Vechol Yisrael Beareihem. And all of Israel ישראל Yisrael in their cities.
So anyway, you have Kohen כהן, Kohen, Levi לוי, Levi, and Yisrael
ישראל. Yisrael. So moving on. Chalalei Gerei Vecharurei חללי גירי וחרורי. Chalalei
Gerei Vecharurei. Chalalim חללים, Chalalim, Gerim גרים Gerim and free slaves. So
chalalim minalan חללים מנלן? chalalim minalan? How do you know chalalim חללים,
chalalim, Kohanim כהנים Kohanim that were born from forbidden unions and therefore
do not have Kedushas Kehuna קדושת כהונה? Kedushas Kehuna? Detanya דתניא, Detanya,
we saw in the Braisa ברייתא. Braisa. Rabbi Yosi Omer רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yosi Omer, Gedola Chazaka גדולה חזקה. Gedola Chazaka. Chazaka חזקה
Chazaka is great, shenemar שנאמר, shenemar, meaning that you can establish something
based on a previous chazaka חזקה chazaka and you keep that status.
Shenemar שנאמר Shenemar as it says, Umibnei Hakohanim Bnei Chavayah Bnei Hakotz
Bnei Barzillai Asher Lakach Mibnos Barzillai Hagiladi Isha Vayikarei Al Shmam ומבני
הכהנים בני חביה בני הקוץ בני ברזלי אשר לקח מבנות ברזלי הגלעדי
אשה ויקרא על שמם. Umibnei Hakohanim Bnei Chavayah Bnei Hakotz Bnei Barzillai
Asher Lakach Mibnos Barzillai Hagiladi Isha Vayikarei Al Shmam. Okay, so these
are the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim that went up with Ezra עזרא, Ezra,
so the sons of Chavayah חביה, Chavayah, the sons of Kotz קוץ,
Kotz, the sons of Barzillai ברזלי. Barzillai. Okay, and these people, they're
called Bnei Barzillai בני ברזלי Bnei Barzillai because these people took from
the daughters of Barzillai ברזלי Barzillai and therefore they were called the
children of Barzillai ברזלי Barzillai even though they were really his daughter's
children. Anyway, these are the families of the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim that
went up from the Gola גולה. Gola. Eleh Bikshu Ksavom Hamisyachasim אלה
בקשו כתבם המתיחשים. Eleh Bikshu Ksavom Hamisyachasim. These, here's the word yichus
יחוס, yichus, these tried to find their books, not their books, whatever,
their records of their yichus יחוס, yichus, of their lineage. Velo Nimtzo-u
ולא נמצאו, Velo Nimtzo-u, and they could not bring documentation about their
lineage to prove that they were like, you know, legitimate Kohanim כהנים.
Kohanim. This is all straight from the pasuk פסוק. pasuk. Vayigo-alu Min
Hakehuna ויגאלו מן הכהונה, Vayigo-alu Min Hakehuna, and they were sort of
exiled, although geulah גאולה geulah normally means redemption, but vayigo-alu ויגאלו vayigo-alu
might be like why she says with an ayin עין ayin to
mean like despised from, they were pushed out from the Kehuna כהונה.
Kehuna. Vayomer Hattirshatha Lahem ויאמר התרשתא להם Vayomer Hattirshatha Lahem and Hattirshatha
התרשתא, Hattirshatha, who is a name for Nechemia נחמיה, Nechemia, said to
them, Asher Lo Yochlu Mikodesh Hakodoshim Ad Amod Kohen Leurim Vetumim אשר
לא יאכלו מקדש הקדשים עד עמד כהן לאורים ולתמים. Asher Lo Yochlu
Mikodesh Hakodoshim Ad Amod Kohen Leurim Vetumim. Now that you have not
been able to demonstrate, to document your Kehuna כהונה, Kehuna, you can
no longer eat from the Kodshei Hakodoshim קדשי הקדשים, Kodshei Hakodoshim, from
presumably the sacrifices, until there is a Kohen Gadol כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol with an Urim Vetumim אורים ותמים, Urim Vetumim, which there was
not in the Second Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, which Rashi
רש"י Rashi says means like saying, you know, until Moshiach משיח. Moshiach.
When Moshiach משיח Moshiach comes maybe you can prove your yichus יחוס,
yichus, but until that time you cannot eat from the Korbanot קרבנות.
Korbanot. Ve-amar Lahem Harei Atem Bechezkaschem ואמר להם הרי אתם בחזקתכם. Ve-amar
Lahem Harei Atem Bechezkaschem. Now, the Gemara גמרא Gemara here is picking
up, this is not the pesukim פסוקים. pesukim. So he said to
them in the pesukim פסוקים pesukim you can't eat from the Korbanot
קרבנות, Korbanot, but now this point that Gedola Chazaka גדולה חזקה, Gedola
Chazaka, which is but you know that they can keep their status
quo. So the point that the Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to
make is although they couldn't eat from the Korbanot קרבנות, Korbanot, but
they could continue eating from the Terumah תרומה Terumah which they were
eating in Chutz La-aretz חוץ לארץ. Chutz La-aretz. And that's Rabbi Yosi's
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi point of Gedola Chazaka גדולה חזקה. Gedola Chazaka.
Because even though they could not document their Kehuna כהונה Kehuna and
they could not eat from the Korbanot קרבנות, Korbanot, they could keep
on presuming they are Kohanim כהנים Kohanim for the purposes on which
because they haven't been disproven to be Kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, there hasn't
been contrary evidence, there's just been a lack of evidence. So they
have a Chazaka חזקה Chazaka of being Kohanim כהנים. Kohanim. All Kohanim
כהנים Kohanim nowadays don't have any evidence that they're Kohanim כהנים. Kohanim.
But about Terumah תרומה? Terumah?
Okay, well that has to do more with tumah טומאה tumah issues,
and we don't have a Chazaka חזקה, Chazaka, they haven't been eating
Terumah תרומה. Terumah. So let's read a little bit more and then
we can discuss. Okay, so the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, okay, they
couldn't prove their Kehuna כהונה Kehuna but it wasn't disproved they were
Kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, so they could continue their status for what it
had been so far. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says Amar Lahem
Harei Atem Bechezkaschem אמר להם הרי אתם בחזקתכם, Amar Lahem Harei Atem
Bechezkaschem, you retain your presumed status. Bameh Hayitem Ochlim Bagola במה הייתם
אוכלים בגולה? Bameh Hayitem Ochlim Bagola? What would you eat in the
exile? Bekodshei Hagvul בקדשי הגבול, Bekodshei Hagvul, with things that were sanctified
you know in the Gvul גבול, Gvul, not in the relating to
the Mikdash מקדש, Mikdash, but relating to all Yisrael ישראל. Yisrael. Now
of course the thing is that outside of Israel ישראל Yisrael anyway
Terumah תרומה Terumah is only rabbinic, but Kodshei Hagvul קדשי הגבול Kodshei
Hagvul means in the, you know, outside of the Beis Hamikdash בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so in Terumah תרומה, Terumah, that's what you've been
eating until now. Af Kan Nami Bekodshei Hagvul אף כאן נמי בקדשי
הגבול, Af Kan Nami Bekodshei Hagvul, here too you could continue eating
Terumah תרומה, Terumah, you retain your Chazaka חזקה, Chazaka, thank you. Okay,
now Ulemandamar Ma'alin Mitrumah Leyichus ולמאן דאמר מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין, Ulemandamar Ma'alin
Mitrumah Leyichus, now we've got a problem though, because there's an opinion
that if you see a
Kohen כהן Kohen eat Terumah תרומה, Terumah, you can presume that he
has a
yichus יחוס. yichus. so someone who's from the כהנים kohanim who can
bring קרבנות korbanot on the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash we'll assume, oh, he's of an equal status, you
know, and they'll sort of intermarry with one another and that'll be
a problem because you now don't want to let these כהנים kohanim
or their descendants eat from the, you know, eat from the קרבנות
korbanot of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but if he eats תרומה,
terumah, he'll be presumed to have that status. So how are we
going to let him eat תרומה? terumah? So the
גמרא Gemara answers: הני דאכלו בתרומה אסוקי מסקינן להו, hani de-achlu be-terumah
assukei maskinan lehu, so if you let them eat תרומה terumah you're
going to raise them up, meaning מעלים, ma'alim, you will and therefore
allow them to eat, to be מקריב makriv the קרבנות. korbanot. So
how can we let them continue to eat תרומה? terumah? In חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz it wasn't a problem, there was no possibility they
would be מקריב קרבנות. makriv korbanot But now they're coming to ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisroel and now you are actually making them at a
lower status, but if you let them eat תרומה, terumah, they'll be
presumed to be at a higher status. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, שאני התם דריע חזקתייהו. shani hasam de-rei'a chezkateihu.
There it's different because their חזקה chazakah has been questioned. Now what
does it mean their חזקה chazakah has been questioned? So רש''י Rashi
says that since other כהנים, kohanim, basically it's been like been made
clear: you guys don't get to eat the קרבנות, korbanot. you guys
do get to, you guys don't get to be מקריב makriv the
קרבנות, korbanot, you guys do get to be מקריב makriv the קרבנות.
korbanot, There already is like a label attached and people understand that
yes, I guess stigmatized is right the way to say it, yeah,
I mean that is more reflective of the word ריע חזקתייהו. rei'a
chezkateihu. So since there was this clear distinction that went on and
says you guys don't get to eat from the קרבנות korbanot. even
though you get to continue eating תרומה, terumah, people understand what the
reality is. Oh, them, they're eating תרומה terumah for a different reason
and they won't make that confusion. That's what רש''י Rashi says. רש''י
Rashi says,
what does רש''י Rashi say? תוספות Tosafot says, oh,
תוספות Tosafot just says because it was known that they looked to
try to find their documentation and couldn't find it. So everybody knew,
were not confused, oh, maybe they are good כהנים, kohanim, because anyway,
so one way or another the point is the historical event made
it clear that they were only eating תרומה terumah and that they
were not כשר כהנים kasher kohanim for other purposes and there was
not that concern that one would lead to the other. Okay, let's
read more and then I'll take the questions. So the גמרא Gemara
so anyway we've got this idea you could continue eating תרומה, terumah,
we're not concerned that you're eating תרומה terumah but you can't be
מקריב makriv קרבנות korbanot because you can't prove you're כהנים, kohanim, and
we're not concerned you're eating תרומה terumah will lead to the other
thing because everybody understands the circumstances. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ואלא מאי גדולה חזקה? ve-ela mai gedolah chazakah? But when
you said גדולה חזקה, gedolah chazakah, it's great, that seems to suggest
that it even goes beyond the previous parameters. Now I don't know
exactly why. It could be that it's great that even though now
we have tried to find documentation and couldn't, or even though now
you know, nevertheless it continues. But the point is that's normally what
חזקה chazakah is. חזקה chazakah is that the status quo continues in
the absence of any evidence. So all we really have here is
no evidence, so of course גדולה חזקה, gedolah chazakah, of course they'll
continue eating תרומה. terumah. So what's
גדולה חזקה? gedolah chazakah? ואלא מאי גדולה חזקה ve-ela mai gedolah chazakah
דמעיקרא אכל בתרומה דרבנן ולבסוף אכל בתרומה דאורייתא. de-me-ikara achal be-terumah de-rabbanan
u-le-basof achal be-terumah de-oraita. Ah, here's the גדולה, gedolah, that even though
in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz it was only rabbinic תרומה terumah because
it's outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, and now they're coming to
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, since they have a status of כהנים kohanim
for eating תרומה, terumah, they'll retain that status vis-à-vis the world of
תרומה terumah even in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel when it becomes תרומה
דאורייתא. terumah de-oraita. So that is a big חידוש, chiddush, right? It's
not like you hairsplit and say you do a hairsplit between תרומה
terumah and קרבנות, korbanot, but that's not so hairsplit. Okay, but within
the world of תרומה, terumah, once they have a חזקה chazakah of
כהנים kohanim vis-à-vis תרומה, terumah, it's for all aspects of
תרומה. terumah. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you want I could
tell you, לעולם התם נמי בדרבנן אכל ובדאורייתא לא אכל. le-olam hasam
nami be-de-rabbanan achal u-ve-de-oraita lo achal. Maybe actually we would hairsplit and
we would say even now that you're coming to ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisroel, you can only eat in rabbinic תרומה terumah in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisroel. What's rabbinic תרומה terumah in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisroel? It's
all ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisroel? So rabbinic תרומה terumah could be these
places that are not sanctified.
But right, so according to
רש''י, Rashi, that's מחלוקת ראשונים, machloket rishonim, which agricultural products are חייב
chayav in תרומה דאורייתא, terumah de-oraita, but רש''י Rashi says that it
is basically only grain, oil, and wine. So according to that, any
type of fruit or whatever would only be תרומה דרבנן. terumah de-rabbanan.
So okay, but if we kept you to limited you to תרומה
דרבנן terumah de-rabbanan in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, what's גדולה חזקה? gedolah
chazakah? So the גמרא Gemara says,
ואיבעית אימא לעולם התם נמי בדרבנן אכל ובדאורייתא לא אכל. le-olam hasam
nami be-de-rabbanan achal u-ve-de-oraita lo achal. Oh, and here we get to
גדולה חזקה. gedolah chazakah. The first point is that answers our previous
question. That will protect us against confusing their status. וכי מסקינן מתרומה
ליוחסין, ve-ki maskinan mi-terumah le-yuchasin, when would I assume that if you're
eating תרומה terumah it means you have full יחוס? yichus? מדאורייתא, mi-de-oraita,
if you eat תרומה דאורייתא. terumah de-oraita. מדרבנן לא מסקינן, mi-de-rabbanan lo
maskinan, not rabbinic. Okay, so now we said they would only eat
rabbinic תרומה terumah in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So now we're not
afraid that it'll lead to a problem with assuming they have full
יחוס. yichus. But the problem then is going to be the next
question. אי הכי מאי גדולה חזקה? ei hachi mai gedolah chazakah? So
what's גדולה חזקה? gedolah chazakah? The חידוש? chiddush? You're continuing to eat
what you ate before; that's standard חזקה. chazaka. So גמרא Gemara says
no: דמעיקרא ליכא למיגזר משום תרומה דאורייתא. demeikara leika lemigzar mishum terumah
d'oraita. When they were eating in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, they could
eat תרומה דרבנן terumah derabbanan and there would be no concern it
would ever lead to any problems because there was no תרומה דאורייתא
terumah d'oraita to be had in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. ולבסוף ulevasof
when they come to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אע"ג דאיכא למיגזר משום
תרומה דאורייתא, af al gav de'ika lemigzar mishum terumah d'oraita, even though
you could say wait, we have to, rabbinically we have to prevent
you from eating the תרומה terumah of fruits in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael because people will see you eat the תרומה terumah of fruits
and next thing you know they'll be eating the תרומה terumah of
grain, which is a very reasonable position. So the point is no,
we're not going to let our rabbinic concerns that one case might
slip to another if it would contravene the חזקה chazaka that you
already have. Okay, nevertheless one minute. אע"ג דאיכא למיגזר משום תרומה דאורייתא,
af al gav de'ika lemigzar mishum terumah d'oraita, בתרומה דרבנן אכל בתרומה
דאורייתא לא אכל. biterumah derabbanan achal biterumah d'oraita lo achal. They could
keep on eating the rabbinic תרומה. terumah. I'm sorry, did I skip
a line?
You just said רבנן אכל בתרומה לא אכל. rabbanan achal biterumah lo
achal.
You said בדאורייתא לא אכל. bed'oraita lo achal. Okay, בדאורייתא לא אכל.
bed'oraita lo achal. Okay, so here was the point anyway. Now what
does this have to do with the fact that they're חללים? challalim?
Meaning it's still a little funny. Remember, the larger point here is
to prove that כהנים חללים kohanim challalim came with them. So far
what we've proven is that כהנים kohanim that cannot prove their יחוס
yichus came with them. But presumably not prove their יחוס, yichus, nowadays
we say how do we know anybody is a כהן? kohen? And
we say the same type of an idea, or everybody has
a חזקה chazaka they can't really prove. There's a presumption. Okay, here
it seems like the question was a little less how do we
know they're כהנים kohanim and more how do we know they're כהנים
כשרים, kohanim kesherim, right? How do we know they're not חללים? challalim?
Right? And there that sort of seemed to be more the issue.
So because basically this whole group of כהנים kohanim that could not
prove they were not חללים challalim came up, that's sort of what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is that's the חללים challalim that came
up. Not like identified as ודאי חללים, vadai challalim, but basically questionable
חללים. challalim. They could not prove that they had a clean כהן
kohen lineage. So since they couldn't prove they had a clean כהן
kohen lineage, they might have been חללים. challalim. They were not allowed
to eat from the קרבנות, korbanot, but because they had a חזקה
chazaka of eating תרומה terumah in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, they were
allowed to continue eating תרומה, terumah, whether תרומה דאורייתא terumah d'oraita or
תרומה דרבנן, terumah derabbanan, but they were allowed to continue eating תרומה,
terumah, which proves the other point which isn't our focus of גדולה
חזקה. gedola chazaka. Yes, Michael.
So what I'm trying to understand is, you know there's חזקה chazaka
like all right, I have a חזקה chazaka sitting in the seat
every day. You know that's חזקה chazaka like תרומה. terumah. You know
if a non-כהן kohen eats תרומה, terumah, the penalty is pretty heavy.
So and also if you look in the תורה, Torah, I mean
at least to me, I mean maybe I'm not seeing it, it
seems like a package deal. You eat תרומה terumah and then you
also eat קדשים, kodashim, where are we, meaning if you're able to.
Right. If you're presumed to be able to eat תרומה, terumah, you're
presumed to be able to eat קרבן. korban. Okay fine, maybe there's
like, you can't
right, like
why and where, based on what, differentiate between one and another.
Okay so the first question is that's the point of גדולה חזקה,
gedola chazaka, that actually is true that you continue to make הלכה
halacha assumptions with huge consequences based on previous status.
You know like I mean the whole beginning of כתובות Ketubot is
a question about a woman who has been a virgin, who is
found not, that she wasn't a virgin, there was a question about
had she committed adultery and not committed adultery, all these different types
of questions. Right, I mean and I mean or question about I
don't know you שחט shacht an animal and you find a nick
in the knife afterwards and when did it get the nick in
the knife, when did the nick whatever, and you say גדולה חזקה
gedola chazaka and you basically permit stuff that might be נבילה. neveilah.
You can go ahead
and have sex even though the woman might be a נדה. niddah.
Yes, גדולה חזקה. gedola chazaka. You make huge הלכה halacha decisions based
on חזקה. chazaka. Now your other question is a good one and
actually ties into this week's פרשה parsha which is אמור, Emor, so
I should say something about that, which is is that normally we
assume that חזקה chazaka is about status and your point is like
make up your mind. Either you say their status is כהנים kohanim
or their status or it's a status of a חלל challal or
non-כהן. kohen. What do you mean you're considered to be a כהן
kohen as far as what we know you've been practicing? So as
far as laws of תרומה terumah are concerned, you have a חזקה
chazaka of a כהן. kohen. As far as these other things you
don't. Now you could say that but it's funny that you are
allowed to apply those different lenses. On the other hand that's the
reality. The חזקה chazaka was established within a certain area and that
maybe the level of proof was the standard of proof was lower
in that area and it's not justified to jump to the other
one. This plays out actually nowadays in this issue about כהנים kohanim
because of the question about when a question comes up about a
כהן kohen marrying let's say a woman who's a גרושה. gerusha. Okay
and the פוסקים poskim have to look for a basis of leniency,
and they sometimes come up with certain ספקות sfekot like meaning
okay so a woman was she really a גרושה? gerusha? Maybe it
wasn't a good קידושין kiddushin to begin with with the first husband?
Not make the kids חללים? challalim?
No no no no, to allow the כהן kohen to, I mean
you could say that, but it starts with to allow the כהן
kohen to marry the presumed כהן kohen to marry the presumed גרושה.
gerusha. Okay. Those cases come up to rabbis a lot. Okay. Okay,
can I marry this woman I just fell in love with? that
she's a גרושה, Grusha, a כהן. Kohen. All right? So often that
goes through two approaches trying to figure out maybe she's not a
גרושה Grusha and maybe you're not a כהן. Kohen. Okay, so maybe
she's not a גרושה, Grusha, you go ahead and you say, well,
you know, I don't know, was the קידושין Kiddushin כשר Kasher to
begin with and and and all of that? But sometimes what goes
into that factor, maybe you're not a כהן Kohen is, oh nowadays
anyway, like how do we really know that anybody is a כהן?
Kohen? Okay, because you know, it's just like a חזקה. Chazakah. So
we're not really sure. So maybe you're not. So this idea of
throwing in that ספק, Safek, you know, I mean it comes up
in other cases, right, like a כהן, Kohen, חס ושלום, Chas V'Shalom,
a כהן's Kohen wife is raped and then there's a question, can
he continue living with her or whatever? How much can you throw
throw in the possibility maybe you're not a כהן? Kohen? So that's
but that does get discussed in the cases of who can a
כהן Kohen marry or stay married to. So the question with Rav
Moshe was dealing with was a case about טומאה. Tumah. And I
by the way, I didn't double check this, so I'm saying this
from memory, so have to double check to make sure the specifics
are correct. But from what I remember, it might have been a
case actually about the הלכה Halacha specifically about a כהן Kohen becoming
a doctor and can he work on a corpse, מטמא למת, Metamei
L'Met, but it was some case of, I think, I'm pretty positive
was that, some case of a כהן Kohen and טומאה. Tumah. And
somebody wanted to make the argument, well, let's use the same question.
We're not really sure I'm a כהן, Kohen, so throw that ספק
Safek into the mix to make it more possible to allow the
כהן Kohen to become טמא. Tamei. So Rav Moshe said there's a
big difference. He said when it comes to getting married, you haven't
really established a חזקה. Chazakah. It's not like you have been now,
you know, throughout your life
not marrying גרושות. Grushot. Like you know, there's like no sense to
that, right? So there's no practice that has demonstrated that in the
world of marriage, you know, in a in a very clear way.
If you've been dating a hundred women and every single one was
discovered to be a גרושה Grusha and then you cut it off,
so that would have demonstrated by your actions that you're a כהן
Kohen in the world of marriage. But that's probably not what happened.
So nothing in your actions demonstrated that within the world of marriage,
you are have established yourself as a כהן. Kohen. But in the
world of טומאה, Tumah, it happens all the time. The כהנים Kohanim
have to avoid things: avoid going to a cemetery, avoid going to
a hospital, avoid this. So your practices have established you as a
כהן Kohen in the world of טומאה Tumah more than they've established
you as a כהן Kohen in the world of marriage. So when
it comes to a טומאה Tumah issue, you really have an established
חזקה Chazakah and you can't play around so much to say, well,
maybe I'm not a כהן. Kohen. So you can't be מיקל. Meikel.
Whereas in the world of marriage, your practice hasn't really established you
as much as a כהן, Kohen, so there maybe there's more to
play around with. Very fascinating way of thinking about that, but that
really reflects exactly what you're saying. Like make up your mind. Do
I have a חזקה Chazakah of being a כהן Kohen or not?
So here we sort of see, you know what? Through the lens
of תרומה דרבנן, Terumah D'Rabbanan, תרומה, Terumah, you have established a practice
of being a כהן. Kohen. Here it's לקולא, L'Kula, I was talking
about whatever לחומרא L'Chumra the other way. But in the world of
קרבנות, Korbanot, there's no practice that's established you so you don't have
that status.
And so we actually do differentiate, you're saying.
Rav Moshe does differentiate, yeah. And here the גמרא, Gemara, you're right,
it's a big חידוש. Chiddush. You would say it's a package deal
but this says no. Through one הלכתי Halachic lens you've established that
status, through another הלכתי Halachic lens you haven't. Charlie gets called on
first because he had his hand up, yeah.
Since
in the level of intermarriage that was described later in ספר עזרא,
Sefer Ezra, it's a it would be surprising if there weren't lots
of חללים Chalalim among the group.
Well, you mean because of all the intermarriage. Right. Well, that's exactly
that's exactly part of the problem. Yeah. Rabbi Dovid?
So it just sounds like, you know, you structure reality through legal
concepts. Sometimes you're going to be satisfied with the
diversity and inner contradictions in a nuanced way and sometimes you're going
to insist that a life be consistent. Right. You go to זריזא?
Zeriza? זריזא? Zeriza? Yep.
Also the נפקא מינה Nafka Mina before is that this guy could
have like a bowl of Cheerios with blueberries in Baghdad but when
he gets to Jerusalem he can only have the blueberries.
Right. Yeah.
One other thing about the about the rabbinic תרומה, Terumah, not all
of their איסור Issur was
related to the...
Right. I had mentioned that too, yes.
But do we then establish this חזקה Chazakah for the kids? Like
let's say the כהן Kohen marries a גרושה, Grusha, then we find
a way but then we don't let these other these kids then
now דוכנ'ן Duchenen or like?
Right. Once you're assuming that is correct. Once you've allowed them to
marry a גרושה Grusha and assume he's not a כהן, Kohen, then
the kids would not be כהנים Kohanim either. I mean מה נפשך
Mah Nafshach they wouldn't. Either he's not a כהן Kohen and they're
ישראלים Yisraelim or he is a כהן Kohen and they're חללים. Chalalim.
Okay, anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. והכתיב, V'Hachtiv, but doesn't
the פסוק Pasuk say: ויאמר התרשתא, Vayomer HaTirshatha, which is נחמיה, Nechemiah,
להם אשר לא יאכלו מקדשי הקדשים? Lahem Asher Lo Yochlu M'Kadshei HaKadashim?
So מקדשי הקדשים M'Kadshei HaKadashim הוא דלא יכל, hu d'lo yachal, הא
כל מידי יכל. ha kol midi yachal. So wait a minute, but
how could you say that it's only דרבנן? D'Rabbanan? It says that
they won't eat from the קדשי קדשים, Kadshei Kadashim, right? But that
means that they could eat from all other things, which presumably includes,
you know, תרומה דאורייתא, Terumah D'Oraisa,
okay? So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכי קאמר: Hachi Ka'amar: לא מידי דמיקרי קודש. lo midi d'mikri kodesh.
Okay, yeah, there you go. So that's תרומה *terumah*. So this is
within the world, this is within the approach that they can't eat
תרומה דאורייתא *terumah de-Oraita*. If they could eat תרומה דאורייתא *terumah de-Oraita*,
the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* is good. Don't eat קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim*,
don't eat קרבנות *korbanot*, but yes eat תרומה *terumah*. But if they
can't eat תרומה דאורייתא *terumah de-Oraita*, קדש קדשים *kodesh kodashim* means קדש
*kodesh* or קדשים *kodashim*. Okay, so don't eat תרומה *terumah*. ולא מידי
דמיקרי קדשים *v'lo midi d'mikri kodashim*. Now קדשים *kodashim* you would think
means קרבנות *korbanot*, but we're actually going to say yes, but even
a lower level of קרבנות *korbanot*. דאמר קרא ובת כהן Kohen, כי
תהיה לאיש זר היא בתרומת הקדשים לא תאכל *d'amar Kra u-bat kohen
ki tihiyeh le-ish zar hi bi-trumat ha-kodashim lo tokhal*. If a בת
כהן bas kohen *bat kohen* is married to a non-כהן kohen *kohen*,
she cannot eat in the תרומת הקדשים *trumat ha-kodashim*, which refers to
the חזה ושוק *chazeh v'shok*, the כהן *kohen*'s portion of the שלמים
*shelamim*. דאמר מר ממורם מן הקדשים *d'amar Mar memuram min ha-kodashim*, something
that is separated from the קרבנות *korbanot*, which means the שלמים *shelamim*.
So a ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael* can eat שלמים *shelamim*, but this is
the חזה ושוק *chazeh v'shok*, the כהן *kohen*'s portion of the שלמים
*shelamim*. Okay, anyway, they cannot eat קרבנות *korbanot*, they can't eat תרומה
*terumah* according to this, תרומה דאורייתא *terumah de-Oraita*, but they could eat
תרומה דרבנן *terumah derabbanan*. לא תאכל *lo tokhal*. Okay, so that's how
you know חללים *challalim*. But again, interestingly, not like established חללים *challalim*,
just ספק חללים *safek challalim*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, גירי וחרורי *geirei v'charurei*, how do you know גרים *geirim*
and freed slaves came up with him? מנלן *minalan*? אמר amar, רב
Rav חסדא אמר amar, קרא *amar Rav Chisda amar Kra*, top of
ע"ב ע"א *Ayin-Beit Amud Alef*, וכל v'chol הנבדל מטומאת גויי הארץ אליהם
*v'khol ha-nivdal mi-tumat goyei ha-aretz aleihem*. And all those that separated themselves
from the impurity of the nations of the land, which basically means
they had been non-Jews. So
how were they non-Jews and now they're not? Either they're converts or
they're freed slaves. Okay, ממזירי ממזירים *mamzeiri mamzeirim*, מנלן *minalan*? דכתיב וישמע
סנבלט החרני וטוביה העבד העמוני *de-khtiv vayishma Sanbalat ha-Choroni v'Tuviyah ha-eved ha-Ammoni*.
So these two people who are non-Jews and one is a slave
heard, וכתב כי רבים ביהודה בעלי שבועה לו *v'khtiv ki rabbim bi-Yehudah
ba'alei shvuah lo*. There were many in Judea that had taken an
oath to this טוביה *Tuviyah* who was a slave. Okay, כי חתן
הוא לשכניה בן ארח *ki chatan hu le-Shechaniah ben Arach*, because he
was a son-in-law to שכניה בן ארח *Shechaniah ben Arach*. So this
slave was a son-in-law to שכניה בן ארח *Shechaniah ben Arach*, who
was a Jew, which means this slave had married this Jewish woman.
Okay, ויהוחנן בנו לקח את בת משלם בן ברכיה *v'Yehochanan beno lakach
et bat Meshullam ben Berechiah*. And יהוחנן *Yehochanan*, the slave's son, had
also married the daughter of this other Jewish man. Okay, so these
slaves, important slaves, slaves of status, whatever, anyway, had married Jewish women
and presumably had children. So those would have been
ממזירים
*mamzeirim*. Now is that really true? A slave and a Jewish woman
is a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*? So the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going to
question it. The גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this, ועבד הבא על
בת ישראל yisrael הולד ממזר mamzer *v'eved ha-ba al bat Yisrael ha-vlad
mamzer*. And if a slave has sex with a בת ישראל *bat
Yisrael*, הולד ממזר mamzer, *ha-vlad mamzer*, דסבר עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על
בת ישראל הולד ממזר *de-savar oved kokhavim v'eved ha-ba al bat Yisrael
ha-vlad mamzer*. And this would be the opinion that the child would
be a ממזר *mamzer*. Why? Because it would be a marriage that
קידושין *kiddushin* isn't binding, so the child would be a ממזר *mamzer*.
We obviously do not פוסק *pasken* that way, right? That's the case
of a child of an intermarriage where the father is not Jewish,
we פוסק *pasken* the child is Jewish and not a ממזר *mamzer*.
Okay, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, הני למאן דאמר הולד ממזר
*hani le-man d'amar ha-vlad mamzer*. That's good if that's your opinion that
because marriage wasn't binding the child was a ממזר *mamzer*. אלא למאן
דאמר הולד כשר *ella le-man d'amar ha-vlad kasher*, but the way we
פוסק *pasken* that the child of that is כשר *kasher*, מאי איכא
למימר *mai ika le-meimar*? What can you say?
Okay, that doesn't prove that ממזירים *mamzeirim* were part of the population.
ותו *v'tu*, ממאי דהוו להו בני *mima'i d'havu lehu bni*? Not
only that, how do you know they had children? It just said
they married these women. How do you know they actually had children
from those marriages? ותו *v'tu*, ממאי דהכא הוו להו וסליקו *mima'i d'hacha
havu lehu v'saliku*? How do you know they had those children in
בבל *Bavel* and came up to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*? Those פסוקים
*pesukim* you just quoted were describing the reality in the land of
Israel. It said ביהודה *bi-Yehudah*, in Judea. Okay, דילמא התם הוו להו
*dilma hatam havu lehu*.
Maybe these marriages occurred in Israel? You were trying to prove that
these were ממזירים *mamzeirim* from בבל *Bavel* that came to ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael*. אלא מהכא *ella me-hacha*, from here. ואלה העולים מתל מלח
Melach, תל חרשא Tel Charsha, כרוב אדון Adon, ואמר *v'eleh ha-olim mi-Tel
Melach, Tel Charsha, Keruv, Addon v'Immer*. These are the following that came
up from the, you know, from these various locations, Tel Melach and
Tel Charsha are locations. Okay, ואמר ולא יכלו להגיד בית אבותם *v'amar
v'lo yachlu le-hagid beit avotam*. They could not say who
their paternal house they were from.
וזרעם *v'zar'am*, and or their זרעם *zar'am*, which רש"י rashi *Rashi* says
means they couldn't tell where they were descendant from, even their mother.
אם ישראל הם *im Yisrael hem*. They couldn't really prove that they
were Jews. Straight פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*, they had a whole part of
the group came up who could not even prove they were Jews.
It didn't say they were non-Jews, they didn't know whether they were
Jewish or not. They couldn't prove they came from a Jewish family.
So now we're going to say, תל מלח Tel Melach, אלו בני
אדם שדומה מעשיהם למעשה סדום Sdom *Tel Melach, elu bnei adam she-domeh
ma'aseihem le-ma'asei Sedom*. So these are people whose deeds are similar to
the deeds of סדום Sdom, *Sedom*. These are people like that their
acts were like the acts of סדום, Sdom, שנהפכו לתל מלח, Shenephchu
letel melach, that they that was overturned into a pillar of salt.
So what does that prove? That proves רש״י Rashi says that according
to certain מדרשים, Midrashim, סדום basically they were known for adultery, and
therefore if a group is compared to the those of סדום, תל
מלח, Melach. what?
מלח, Melach, right, salt, yeah.
What did I say?
No, we're saying מלח.
melach, No, I was trying to say מלח, if I mispronounced it.
Okay, anyway, okay, I'm sorry if I mispronounced it. All right, anyway,
so they are anyway, so they're like סדום, so they had committed
adultery, which means their kids were ממזרים. Mamzerim. So based on that
דרשה, Drasha, I mean the the פסוק pasuk emphasizes that they didn't
know that they were from that they were Jews. They couldn't prove
that they were Jews. But the דרשה Drasha is that actually the
first group is is that they were ממזרים, Mamzerim, that they came
from a place which was rife with adultery. תל חרשא, tel charasha.
זה שקורא אבא ואימא ואימא משתקת
אותו. ze shekore Abba ve'Imma ve'Imma meshateket oto. That's the חרשא Charsha
means like חרש, Cheresh, silence. So the guy can't say daddy, daddy.
That's a שתוקי. Shtuki. That's a שתוקי. Shtuki. So we're going to
use this פסוק pasuk to to get ממזרים, Mamzerim, שתוקים, Shtukim, and
אסופים. Asufim. Okay? So we've answered, we've dealt with the remainder of
the list of the משנה. Mishna. Okay?
So so he says so it says daddy, daddy and mom says
shh, be quiet. Okay. ולא יוכלו להגיד בית אבותם וזרעם אם מישראל
הם, Velo yuchlu lehagid beit avotam vezaram im miYisrael hem, זהו האסופי.
zehu ha'asufi.
And the last one is like they couldn't prove at all, you
know, that they were from Israel, right? The person who doesn't know
who his father is still knows he's from Israel, he's from he's
a Jew, he's from Israel. But the third group couldn't even prove
that they were Jewish. They didn't even know who their mother was.
Okay, that's the אסופי, asufi, that's the foundling, שנאסף מן השוק. sheneesaf
min hashuk.
Well now דרשה, drasha, כרוב אדון ואימר.
Kruv Adon ve'Imar. Well now we're going to have the דרשה. drasha.
But the first point is that that פסוק pasuk allows us to
include, right, ממזרים, Mamzerim,
שתוקים, Shtukim, and and אסופים. Asufim. And the נתינים Netinim by the
way, we didn't explicitly point it out, but you remember the the
נתינים Netinim appeared explicitly in a פסוק earlier. So we've got the
whole list now. Okay, now we're going to do a דרשה. drasha.
כרוב אדון ואימר, Kruv Adon ve'Imar, אמר רבי אבהו, amar Rabbi Abbahu,
אמר, okay, אמר אדון אני, amar Adon ani, אמר אדון. amar Adon.
So the master said, God said, so it's אדון, אני אמרתי, ani
amarti, I said, יהיו ישראל לפני חשובים ככרוב, yehu Yisrael lefanai chashuvim
ke-Kruv, that the Israel should be as important to me like the
cherubs, like the angels. Okay, not like a gourd. Okay, like the
cherubs. They what? Cabbage, right. והם שמו עצמם כנמר. vehem samu atzmam
ke-namer. So this is probably finding what אימר, Imar, אימר, imer, right,
אימר imer that they made themselves like what's a נמר? namer? A
leopard? A leopard, right, you know, like a distrustful, you know, the
leopard changed its spots or something, although it can't change its spots,
it's true. Anyway, well somebody actually told me I somebody my I
have my nephew who is Israeli just used a word to to
say like like a hypocrite in in in Hebrew I think was
was what was it? Is it מנומר? menumar? No.
מנומר Menumar is spotted.
No, spotted. What what was it?
צבוע. Tzavua. What? Yeah. צבוע. Tzavua.
צבוע Tzavua is also a a jackal.
A jackal. Aha, yeah, so it was similar type of an animal.
Anyway, okay. So anyway, they made themselves like these untrustworthy animals. They
go ahead and they commit adultery and so on. So you know,
and have and intermarry and all of that. So that's the, you
know, the God's commentary on that reality. Okay, כנמר. ke-namer. איכא דאמרי,
Ika de'amri, some
say, אמר רבי אבהו, amar Rabbi Abbahu,
אמר אדון, amar Adon, the master said, God said, אף על פי
ששמו עצמן כנמר, af al pi shesamu atzman ke-namer, even though they
made themselves like a leopard, even though they acted in this untrustworthy
way and inappropriate way, הן חשובים לפני ככרוב, hen chashuvim lefanai ke-Kruv,
they retain their I you know their status before me, I love
them still, they're as important as as the cherubs. Slightly different דרשה,
drasha, right? Which way you end? אמר רבא בר בר חנה. Amar
Rabba bar bar Chana. Now, this is a פסוק that's going to
be important because now the גמרא Gemara is going to have a
I can't call it really Agadic, it's sort of it's a values
digression about talking about this problem of ייחוס. yichus. And you know
and now we really sort of confront these this issue, like the
sort of an egalitarian ethos, you know, about like who really cares
who your parents are, it's all about like what you've accomplished and
so on, especially the world of תורה. Torah. Like there's a world
about that you don't, you know, the famous משנה Mishna in הוריות,
Horayot, which is which is exactly built on this sort of question
about hierarchy and status, it's like, you know, it's like who do
you save first? You know, כהן, then לוי, Levi, then ישראל, you
know, כהן קודם ללוי, Kohen kodem le-Levi, לוי קודם לישראל, Levi kodem
le-Yisrael, ישראל קודם לנתין, Yisrael kodem le-Natin, נתין קודם לממזר. Natin kodem
le-mamzer. You know, it goes through this whole list, essentially reflecting our
משנה. Mishna. But then it says אימתי, Eimatai, says the משנה, Mishna,
בזמן שכולם שוין. bizman shekulam shavin. But
if you have a ממזר who's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, it's
קודם לכהן גדול עם הארץ. kodem le-Kohen Gadol am ha'aretz. Which basically
means that the world of תורה Torah is the you know is
the sort of equalizer, is fundamentally egalitarian in its and it's based
on your accomplishment within תורה. Torah. None of these issues really matter,
right? So you have very different ethos from like the rabbinic תורה
Torah world from like the the בית המקדש beis hamikdash כהן לוי
levi ישראל hierarchy world. So it's interesting to know, right, how is
the גמרא Gemara going to approach this משניות mishnayos and these reality
that is bringing on all of these issues of hierarchy? Right? Now
some of it you could say has really like halakhic נפקא מינה.
nafkaminas. Obviously ממזר still a problem. But other types of things, like
is it important, should I try to marry a בת כהן bas
kohen, or should I marry a בת תלמיד חכם? bas talmid chacham?
Right, the גמרא Gemara, is clear you'd better to marry a בת
תלמיד חכם bas talmid chacham than to marry a בת כהן, right?
You know, but what if some so keeping that in mind it's
going to be interesting 'cause the אגדתא agadatas we're going to read
or the passages we're going to read are going to be very
in line with the ethos of this משנה mishnah and not what
I would sort of consider the normal rabbinic תורה Torah type of
ethos. You know, תלמוד תורה talmud torah ethos. So let's take a
look. עדיות, eduyos, עדיות. eduyos. Yeah, no, no, no, it's הוריות. horayos.
No. I always get those confused. No, no, no, it's not עדיות.
eduyos. It's הוריות. horayos. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה: amar rabbah
bar bar chana: כל הנושא אשה שאינה הגונה לו, kol hanosei ishah
she'einah hogenas lo, anybody who marries a woman that is not fitting
for him. Now you could say maybe she doesn't have the right
מדות, midos, but it's clear from the context that it means she's
of a lower יחוס yichus than he is. Okay. מעלה עליו הכתוב
כאילו חרשו לכל העולם כולו וחרשו לכל העולם כולו וזרעו מלח. ma'aleh
alav hakatuv k'ilu charasho l'chol ha'olam kulo v'chasho l'chol ha'olam kulo v'zara'o
melach. That it's like he מלח, I did that again. Okay. It's
like he plowed the entire
world and plowed it and planted it with salt, so destroyed the
entire world. Like you plow and then you pour salt in, you
destroy the land. Okay, like he destroyed the entire world. שנאמר: shene'emar:
ואלה העולים מתל מלח מלח, ve'eleh ha'olim mitel melach melach, I did
that again, תל חרשא. charasha So here we're reading the חרשא as
word of plowing, okay? So here these people that were of a
lower social status or יחוס yichus status and it's like the whole
world has been plowed over and plowed in with salt. אמר רבה
בר בר אבא אמר רב: amar rabbah bar bar avada amar rav:
It's like you're ruining the person,
it's like you're ruining the person of that state...
well, I don't know, it's also look, preventing any seeds
from growing.
That's what it is. The whole idea of, right, the whole idea
of, right, about about I mean you know by the way what
the word for farming is? Is husbandry, right? The whole analogy of
plowing and planting seeds, I'm serious, and sends something to the, right,
this
sounds like chorus.
What? Well, yeah, but that's the point I mean.
Husbandry is I thought raising animals, no?
Oh, is it?
I thought husbandry was raising cattle.
Oh, maybe you're right. We'll have to check that. ספריא sefaria can
check for that. But anyway, but either way, either way, the point
is the idea, yes, about plowing and planting seeds and children going
forth. It's all very much about, you know, this metaphor for
marriage and for children and so on. So you are creating and
perpetuating sort of, you know, spreading in the world this lower class
of people, these people of lesser יחוס yichus which is destroying the
world. Okay. So making the world, right, barren. שנאמר, shene'emar, okay. אמר
רבה בר בר אבא אמר רב: amar rabbah bar bar avada amar
rav: כל הנושא אשה לשום ממון, kol hanosei ishah l'shum mamon, anybody
that marries a woman for money. Now again in the context what
רש"י Rashi says this means is why would you marry somebody of
lower social status? Well, maybe she's very wealthy. Right? Why would somebody
go down in status, you know, in terms of who they're marrying?
It could be they fell in love, but okay, let's ignore that.
Very often, you know, you have these classes in England, right, the
upper classes that were like impoverished, right? And then the question is,
do you marry a lower class that's a wealthy lower, you know,
somebody from lower class who's very wealthy? All right, so anyway, הוו
לו בנים שאינם הגונים. havyu lo banim she'einam hogenin. So here again
it's about the children. The children will turn out improper.
שנאמר: shene'emar: בה' בגדו כי בנים זרים ילדו. baHashem bagadu ki banim
zarim yaladu. They rebelled against God because they had foreign children. So
and we'll see in the end how we tie it into this
idea of money. But this means that the result also of you
know of of going to this lower class leads to actually bad
character. Now by the way the גמרא cannot say that it's אסור
assur across the board to marry somebody from a lower social class
'cause there are people in the lower social class, who are they
supposed to marry? Right? So the best we can hope for is
to not get things any worse. So to keep people from the
higher social class marrying among themselves, right? So that's sort of why
the emphasis is don't go to this lower social class.
ושמא תאמר ממון פלט, v'shema tomar mamon palat, maybe you'll say okay
but you know the kids turn out bad but at least you
know you married for money, at least you'll be able to be
wealthy, your money will be saved. תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: עתה יאכלם
חדש את חלקיהם. atah yochlem chodesh es chelkehem. Now even in a
month will be destroyed their portion. ושמא תאמר חלקו, v'shema tomar chelko,
maybe yours, the money, the man who married this woman who was
more wealthy, the man's money will be destroyed, ולא חלקה v'lo chelka
but not the money she got from her family? תלמוד לומר: talmud
lomar: חלקיהם, chelkehem, their portion. ושמא תאמר לזמן מרובה, v'shema tomar l'zman
merubeh, fine it'll take a long time before their money goes you
know gets to goes to waste? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: חדש, chodesh,
in a month.
מאי משמע? mai mashma? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: amar rav nachman
bar yitzchak: חדש נכנס וחדש יצא. chodesh nichnas v'chodesh yatza. ואמר רבה
בר רב אדא
אמר ליה אמר רב סלא אמר רב המנונא
v'amar Rabba bar
Rav Adda amar lei amar Rav Sala amar Rav Hamnuna כל הנושא
אשה שאינה הוגנת לו, kol hanoseh isha she'eina hogenet lo, anybody who
marries a woman that is not deserving to fit for him, again
in terms of social status, אליהו כופתו, Eliyahu kofato, Eliyahu binds him
up against like the post, והקדוש ברוך הוא רוצעהו, v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu
rotzehu, and God is the one that gives him lashes. Okay. ותנא
על כולם אליהו כותב והקדוש ברוך הוא חותם, v'tana al kulam Eliyahu
kotev v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu chotem, and we learned in another Baraita on
all of them אליהו Eliyahu writes the following writ and God signs
it, אוי לו לפוסל את זרעו, oi lo l'posel et zaro, woe
to he who, you know,
invalidates his children, you know, stigmatizes his children, so again it's about
the children that are that are born, והפוגם את משפחתו, v'hapogem et
mishpachto, and stigmatizes his family,
והנושא אשה שאינה הוגנת לו, v'hanoseh isha she'eina hogenet lo, and who
marries a woman that is not fit for him. So basically God
has now, you know, will give you your punishment and, you know,
and proclaim your the the evil of what you have done. Okay.
So the next four words are just repeating it seems the הגה
Hagah strikes them out, אליהו כותב והקדוש ברוך הוא רוצעהו. Eliyahu kotev
v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu rotzehu. Okay. וכל הפוסל, v'chol haposel, and this seems
to now be continued what is sort of written in this writ
that אליהו Eliyahu writes and God signs. Interesting why we pick אליהו.
Eliyahu. Some say what does אליהו Eliyahu do like אליהו, Eliyahu, you
know, אליהו Eliyahu is up in heaven, you know, and אליהו Eliyahu
also, you know, he is up there alive in heaven, and אליהו
Eliyahu is the one who is you know, you know, who is
נוקם נקמת השם, nokem nikmat Hashem, you know, when God says אליהו
Eliyahu what are you doing here, right? And he says, you know,
you know, everybody betrayed your trust and I remain faithful. So he
he is the one that ensures not necessarily about עבירות aveirot but
that everybody is sort of like remaining faithful. Okay. ההוא גברא hahu
gavra and וכל הפוסל פסול ואינו מדבר בשבחו לעולם. v'chol haposel pasul
v'eino medaber b'shivcho l'olam. Now it's not clear if this is בשבח
b'shevach or בשבחו b'shivcho לעולם. l'olam. Anyway, it's not clear if this
is part of the writ that אליהו Eliyahu is writing or this
is now the גמרא speaking. But anybody who invalidates, right, who basically,
you know, who says, but now we're sort of switching. Okay, this
is if it actually occurs it's disastrous. But if somebody goes around
and claims that somebody, "Oh you, I know you, you know, your
father was a ממזר, oh you, your family was so-and-so," somebody that
goes and tries to, if God writes the writ and if אליהו
Eliyahu writes the writ and God signs it, okay, then that then
we know that that family is a problem. But there's a difference
between saying that the family is a problem and saying now that
everybody is going to go and try to stigmatize, you know, if
you actually do we how do we treat rumors and claims that
people say in a world in which we're highly sensitive to status
issues which is what this is describing, or maybe the problem is
we weren't so sensitive and חז״ל Chazal are trying, at least the
the בעל ba'al of this מימרא memra is trying to get people
more sensitivity than they were? You don't have to give these exhortations
if everybody's already being careful about it, okay. But we're trying so
in a world which has this sensitivity and maybe according to this
גמרא trying to heighten this sensitivity to these issues about יחוס yichus
and status, you can also imagine that an easy way to defame
somebody is to claim something about them and their family status. So
the counterbalance to this is, it's true, it's terrible if you do
this thing about going like lowering your class, intermarrying with a family
that has a lower status. But if you claim that about somebody,
right, then that and without and it's not known and there's no
evidence, וכל הפוסל פסול, v'chol haposel pasul, you yourself are invalid.
So וכל means however?
No, I was reading it like that, anyone who is פוסל. posel.
But the ו, vav, right?
Oh, oh yeah, the ו vav is however.
The ו vav is however.
Right, the ו vav is however. Right, right, right, right, right, right.
Right. Exactly. Okay, the ו, vav, right. And however, anybody who invalidates
is פסול, pasul, right I hear you, but is in self-invalid, ואינו
מדבר בשבחו לעולם v'eino medaber b'shivcho l'olam or בשבח לעולם. b'shevach l'olam.
Anyway, it's not clear if this is the first statement is invalid
because you're always just criticizing, you never find anything nice to say
about people. You know, what's that what's the saying? If you don't
have anything nice, don't say anything at all.
Okay. But ואמר שמואל, v'amar Shmuel, Shmuel takes it one step further
and says במומו פוסל. b'mumo posel. If you're invalidating somebody else, that's
only because that's a problem that you have in yourself. כל, kol,
so that normally is conflated, the middle is taken out, and you'll
hear the classic phrase כל הפוסל במומו פוסל. kol haposel b'mumo posel.
Anybody who invalidates others, it's because they have that problem in themself.
Okay, which is what what is that? The pot calling the kettle
black type of a thing. Yes.
So this means all these rabbis who are פוסלין poslin converts are
themselves not Jewish?
No. So the question is if you've got, well, good point. We're
going to see even with this statement having been made that the
rabbis still got up and would declare this family is פסולה psula
and that family is פסולה. psula. So you know if you're like
if that's your your job to actually investigate. identify and clarify, you
know the point is here you're doing it as just calling people
names or spreading unfounded rumors, right? You know, so but obviously as
we've been seeing, I mean Ezra went and he identified all the
different families, right? All the different groups. So it's not sort of
saying that nobody should be doing that job, you know, but it's
sort of saying not every layperson gets to say oh you know,
this guy's פסול pasul and that guy's פסול pasul and so on.
Okay.
So let's take a look.
Okay. Now we're going to have a great story which eventually will
circle back to this idea about about כל הפוסל במומו פוסל, kol
haposul bemumo posul, but it's a good it and it does a
lot of other things along the way. ההוא גברא דמן נהרדעא, Hahu
gavra demin nehardea, a certain person from Nehardea, דעל בבי מטבחיא בפומבדיתא.
de'al beve mitbachaya bepumbedisa.
He was visiting Pumbedisa and he went to the butcher to buy
some meat. ואמר להו, Va'amar lehu, and he said to them, the
people in the butcher store, הבו לי בישרא, havu li bisra, give
me a piece of meat. Okay, אמרו ליה, amru leh, they said
to him, נטר עד דשקיל
לשמעיה דרב יהודה בר יחזקאל מנסב לך. nater ad deshakeil leshamayei derav
yehuda bar yechezkel menaseiv lach. You know what, we'll get you in
a minute, you know, but we first have to take care of
the servant, the attendant of Rav Yehuda bar יחזקאל Yechezkel is here
and we got to take care of we you know we're going
to sort of serve him first, okay, and then we'll give to
you. So he was very offended. What do you mean I got
here first? Why are you giving him? I got here first! So
אמר, מאן יהודה בר שביסקל דקדים לי? man yehuda bar sheviskel dekadim
li? So he made fun of the guy's name, okay? He said
bar יחזקאל, Yechezkel, this is Rav Yehuda, the classic Rav Yehuda of
the גמרא, okay? So he said, who is this Yehuda bar שביסקל?
Sheviskel? יחזקאל, Yechezkel, שביסקל. Sheviskel. Anyway רש"י Rashi also says that שביסקל
sheviskel could also mean like a glutton. He needs his meat, he's
got to get go up first, who is this Yehuda the son
of a glutton? Okay, דקדים לי, dekadim li, that gets to go
before me, דשקיל מן קמאי, deshakeil min kamai, that can take before
I get to take. So אזלו אמרו ליה לרב יהודה, azlu amru
leh lerav yehuda, so they told Rav Yehuda, you know this guy,
this visitor
from Nehardea just like offended you, like you know he just insulted
you.
שמתיה, Shamtay, so Rav Yehuda put him in חרם. cherem. Okay, put
him in נידוי. niduy. As רש"י says, somebody who you know who
disgraces or shows
who shows
disregard for תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, you know, asks in a disrespectful
way should be put in חרם cherem or נידוי. niduy. Right, the
guy who was yelling. He offended Rav, I mean not a personal
offense, but he you know he showed disrespect to a big תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham so Rav Yehuda put him in נידוי. niduy. אמרו,
Amru, then they said to Rav Yehuda, לגב דקרי אינשי עבדי, legav
dekarei inshi avdi, you know this guy goes around and anybody he
you can tell he's a hothead, right? So anybody who offends him
he says oh you're a slave, you're a slave. Okay. So אכזי
ליה דעבדא הוא, achzeih leh de'avda hu, so Rav Yehuda then proclaimed,
this guy's a slave. Okay, this is based on the principle of
כל הפוסל במומו פוסל. kol haposul bemumo posul. If he's going around
calling everybody a slave, must be that he's a slave. Okay, now,
אזל ההוא, azal hahu, so this guy, this customer, this visitor who
now has been declared to be a slave by Rav
Yehuda went ואזמניה לדינא קמיה דרב נחמן. ve'azminei ledina kemei derav nachman.
He called Rav Yehuda to a בית דין beis din to judgment
to Rav Nachman. Now Rav Nachman is back in his hometown in
Nehardea. Okay. So this guy now wants Rav Yehuda who's this major
authority in Pumbedisa to come to a בית דין beis din in
Nehardea where he's going to you know he's going to you know
call him to דין din because he offended him, because he called
him a slave. Okay.
So ואזמניה לדינא קמיה דרב נחמן. ve'azminei ledina kemei derav nachman. אייתי
פתקא דאזמנא, Aysei pitka de'azmana,
so Rav Yehuda took the the writ, the subpoena, the writ, the
subpoena, right, of being called to a בית דין. beis din. אזל
רב יהודה קמיה דרב הונא. Azal rav yehuda kemei derav huna. He
went to Rav Huna. Okay. Off in you know they're still they're
in Pumbedisa there. Okay. This guy went back to Nehardea. He went
to Rav Huna and he said, אמר ליה, amar leh, איזיל או
לא איזיל? eizal o lo eizal? Should I go ahead and now
and go to Nehardea to stand in front of a בית דין
beis din with this with Rav Nachman? So אמר ליה, amar leh,
מיזל לא מיבעי לך למיזל. meizil lo miba'ei lach lemeizil. Halachically you
are not required to go or not only not required you shouldn't
go and really in principle. משום דגברא רבא את. Mishum degavra raba
at. You are a great person and presumably you're greater than Rav
Nachman. It's an interesting halachic question, I mean even great people can
get called to a בית דין, beis din, but also I mean
I would imagine that part of the problem is is that Rav
Nachman is out of his what do you call it
jurisdiction. Right. Anyway you really shouldn't have no need to go. אלא
משום יקרא דבי נשיא, Ela mishum yekara devei nesia, but Rav Nachman
is however a son-in-law of the house of the נשיא, nasi, so
you know, so out of respect for that and part of the
whole problem here was an issue of who's paying respect to who,
out of respect for that, קום זיל, kum zil, you should go,
go fine, go to the בית דין beis din for Rav Nachman.
Now clearly Rav Yehuda was not happy that he was going to
have to make this not only make the trip but you know
submit himself. to the authority of רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman*,
when anyway the whole point was he was standing up for the
right for his authority to be respected. So he's going to have
some interesting interactions with רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* when he
gets there. Okay, so אזל אשכחיה דקעביד מעקא *Azal Ashkachei De-Ka Avid
Ma'aka*. So he went and he saw that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
*Rav Nachman* was making a fence. So אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar
Lei*, "לא סבירא ליה למר להא דאמר רב הונא בר אידי אמר
שמואל Shmuel כיון שנתמנה אדם פרנס על הציבור אסור בעשיית מלאכה בפני
שלושה *Lo Savra Lei Le-Mar Le-Ha De-Amar Rav Huna Bar Idi Amar
Shmuel Keivan She-Nitmana Adam Parnas Al Ha-Tzibur Assur Be-Asiyas Melacha Bifnei Shlosha*?"
So now the whole interaction is going to be that רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda, *Rav Yehuda* is going to be showing up רב נחמן
Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* that רב נחמן Rav Nachman. *Rav Nachman* has
no right to call him to a בית דין beit din! *Beis
Din* that he's like, you know, nothing compared to רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda *Rav Yehuda*. Okay, so anyway, so he said to רב נחמן
*Rav Nachman*, he says, "I don't understand, don't you know the teaching
of שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*?" Now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda, *Rav Yehuda* was
a classic student of שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel* also. "Don't you know the
teaching of שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* that once a person is created, given
a position of an office over the, you know, the community, he
should not go ahead and like mow his own lawn, right? That's
not respectful to the office, which is what this was all about,
right? Respect of the office and protecting the office. So here what
are you doing making your own fence? You know, once you're a
פרנס על הציבור *Parnas Al Ha-Tzibur*, once you're in a position of
authority, you don't do common labor in the presence of other people."
אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar Lei*, right, it's a big question about
rabbis, right? Do you want your congregants to see you mowing the
lawn, going shopping, and all those types of things? What? Jogging? Right.
Although that has more to do with attire maybe, but anyway, okay,
how do you maintain that status vis-a-vis the ציבור *Tzibur*? So he
says, אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar Lei*, "פורצא דגונדריתא הוא דקא עבידנא
*Portza De-Gundirisa Hu De-Ka Avidna*." What do you mean? I'm just doing
a like I'm just like fixing a little little break here. I'm
not building the fence, okay, or making a little thing, like he
was minimizing what he was doing. But the point was, was that
the word he used for fence now was גונדריתא *Gundirisa*, which is
not a common word for fence. So אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar
Lei*, "מי סני מעקה דכתיב באורייתא *Mi Sani Ma'ake De-Kasiv Be-Oraisa*?" I
don't understand why you use this weird word גונדריתא *Gundirisa*. What's the
problem with the Torah's word מעקה *Ma'ake*, a fence, או מחיצה דאמרו
רבנן rabbanan, *O Mechitza De-Amru Rabbanan*, or the Rabbinic word? Now part
of this is going to be not just that he like is
that the language presumably he was using was a little bit of
a highfalutin language, seems to be the point. So it's an interesting
mix, like, you know, you're, you know, you're holding yourself of this
high status, you think you can call me in front of you,
and on the one hand you're like, you know, doing stuff that
you should not be doing, like you're doing stuff that that is
not respectful of your own status and office, you're building this fence.
And on the other hand you're taking on airs that is being
a little, you know, that is also that is inappropriate.
I don't read it that way. I actually thought the opposite. He's
using the common vernacular.
Well, let's because
I'm reading it that way because I know the rest of the
story. So let's keep on reading, okay? All right. So
okay, אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar Lei*, so then רב נחמן *Rav
Nachman* said to him, he said to him, you know, "יתיב מר
אקרפיתא *Yisiv Mar A-Karpisa*. Why don't you sit on the stool?" אמר
ליה Amar lei, *Amar Lei*, "ומי סני ספסל דאמרו רבנן rabbanan. *U-Mi
Sani Safsal De-Amru Rabbanan*? Why do you call it a קרפיתא *Karpisa*?
Either call it a stool, ספסל *Safsal*, which the rabbis call it,
או אצטבא דאמרי אינשי *O Itztaba De-Amrei Inshi*, or there's the vernacular,
an אצטבא *Itztaba*, which is what people say." אמר ליה Amar lei,
*Amar Lei*, "ליכול מר אתרונגא *Leichol Mar Estrunga*. Why don't you have
some אתרונגא *Estrunga*?" אמר ליה *Amar Lei*, "הכי אמר שמואל Hachi amar
Shmuel, כל האומר אתרונגא תילתא ברמות רוחא *Hachi Amar Shmuel Kol Ha-Omer
Estrunga Tilta Be-Ramus Ruacha*." See, I knew the end of the story.
Has a third of haughtiness in them. או אתרוג כדקרי רבנן *O
Esrog Ke-Dekari Rabbanan*, either use the word אתרוג *Esrog*, which is a
Rabbinic word, או אתרוגא דאמרי אינשי *O Esroga De-Amrei Inshi*, but what's
this extra 'nun', אתרונגא *Estrunga*? So you're speaking on the one hand,
you know, you're putting on these airs and you're using this highfalutin
language, and on, you know, and you think you can call me
to a בית דין beit din? *Beis Din*, and you're taking too
many airs for your, you know, too much haughtiness for yourself. And
on the other hand, you're, you know, what, building this fence in
public? Yeah.
Wait, wait,
it's doing the opposite of what was suggested in the sense that
he was, רב הונא *Rav Huna* was saying, you know, you should
for the sake of the honor of the office you shouldn't go.
Right, instead he's degrading him.
Yeah, I don't know if it's degrading as much as showing him
up, but yes, I do understand. He was not happy that he
had to go, right? Exactly,
exactly. He was making this point to show "I'm here but I
don't really should be here", right, that was clearly it. Yeah.
קרפיתא *Karpisa* and אצטבא *Itztaba* were Greek, ספסל *Safsal* is
Latin, and אתרונגא *Estrunga* is an Iranian cognate for אתרוג *Esrog*, according
to Steinsaltz.
So they're all loanwords. So they're all loanwords. Okay, fine. Okay. אמר
ליה *Amar Lei*, "לישתי מר אנבגא *Lishti Mar Anvaga*. Why don't you,
why don't you come and have some אנבגא *Anvaga*?" אמר ליה *Amar
Lei*, "מי סני איספרגוס דקריוה רבנן *Mi Sani Ispargos De-Karyuha Rabbanan*?" I
know, we want to say asparagus, but apparently it's some type of
a drink, of a health drink. And a Greek word. או אנפק
דאמרי אינשי *O Anfak De-Amrei Inshi*, or this other word that is
the vernacular word? What are you again using these fancy words? אמר
ליה *Amar Lei*, okay, phew, I'm just trying to be a nice
host, everything I say you, okay. אמר ליה *Amar Lei*, "תיתי דונג
תשקינן *Taysi Dunag Tashkinan*. Let דונג *Dunag*, my daughter, come and pour
us a drink of wine." אמר ליה *Amar Lei*, "הכי אמר שמואל
*Hachi Amar Shmuel*..." which שמואל *Shmuel* says, אין משתמשים
באשה *Ein Mishtamshin Be'ishah*. They're not allowed to—no, that's the next side.
They're not allowed to use the services of a woman. Now that
could be because it's inappropriate for men to be using the services
or רש״י *Rashi* says it's inappropriate for the women to learn to
be too much in the company of men. Anyway, so he says,
קטנה *Ketannah*? What do you mean? She's a minor! She's just a
kid! So, no. בפירוש אמר שמואל אין משתמשים באשה כלל, בין גדולה
בין קטנה *Beperush Amar Shmuel Ein Mishtamshin Be'ishah Klal, Bein Gedolah Bein
Ketannah*. So clearly, you know, you're again highfalutin and at the same
time you're not respectful enough of your office and you don't know
enough הלכה *Halachah* anyway. Okay. So he says, נשדר ליה מר שלמא
לילתא *Neshader Lei Mar Shelama Leyalta*? Would you like to—would you like
to send your respects to my wife, ילתא Yalta, *Yalta*? This is
what רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* is saying to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
*Rav Yehuda*. אמר ליה *Amar Lei*, הכי אמר שמואל *Hachi Amar Shmuel*,
כל באשה ערוה *Kol Be'ishah Ervah*. How can I go and greet
your wife? I will hear her responding and כל באשה ערוה *Kol
Be'ishah Ervah*. Now this is important because people assume כל באשה ערוה
*Kol Be'ishah Ervah* means the singing voice, but the גמרא *Gemara* never
says that. The גמרא *Gemara* says the voice of a woman is
ערוה *Ervah*. The ראשונים *Rishonim* say nowadays that we have become accustomed
to, you know, there's more intermingling with men and women, so we
actually sometimes do speak to one another, so we have become accustomed
to women's speaking voice. It's only the singing voice is an ערוה
*Ervah*, which is important because it shows that those categories of כל
באשה ערוה *Kol Be'ishah Ervah*, whatever, are not absolute. They can change
based on cultural context: what you are used to hearing and not
used to hearing, used to seeing and not used to seeing, and
so on. Very important and things like שער באשה ערוה *Sa'ar Be'ishah
Ervah*, right? The ערוך השלחן *Aruch Hashulchan*, משנה ברורה *Mishnah Berurah* say
that once women aren't covering their hair, right? It's not like it's
אסור *Assur* to דאוון *Daven* anymore in front of a woman who
has uncovered hair. Okay, which doesn't necessarily mean it's מותר *Mutar*, whatever,
that's a separate question. I mean it's מותר *Mutar* for a married
woman—not to, but in terms of whether it's considered an ערוה *Ervah*.
So anyway, here it's clear that כל באשה ערוה *Kol Be'ishah Ervah*
meant speaking voice. How can I greet her? She'll say something back.
שמואל *Shmuel* says כל באשה ערוה *Kol Be'ishah Ervah*. Okay. So he
says אפשר על ידי שליח *Efshar Al Yedei Shaliach*. Okay, so don't
do it yourself, but send somebody to—to—to say hello to her. אמר
ליה *Amar Lei*, הכי אמר שמואל *Hachi Amar Shmuel*, אין שואלים בשלום
אשה *Ein Sho'alin Bishlom Ishah*. You don't even through an intermediary ask
after the well-being of a—of a married woman, because it'll create inappropriate,
you know, sense of—who knows what will come of that. So next
thing you know it'll lead to mixed dancing. So he says—he says,
אפשר על ידי בעלה *Efshar Al Yedei Ba'alah*. What do you mean?
How about—how about through me? I, you know, ask me to—to ask
after well-being. You know, רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* was here, he sent
his best. So אמר ליה *Amar Lei*, הכי אמר שמואל *Hachi Amar
Shmuel*, אין שואלים בשלום אשה כלל *Ein Sho'alin Bishlom Ishah Klal*. You
don't ask after the well-being of a woman—you know, of a wife
at all, even through her husband, because even through her husband, they
say, what could be—husband's part of it? No. We're afraid that innuendo,
it'll lead to one thing to another. Now תוספות *Tosafot*, of course,
asks, what about the fact that the מלאכים *Malachim* say, איה שרה
אשתך *Ayeh Sarah Ishtecha*? So—what? והא מלאכים *Veha Malachim*? So I don't
know, I didn't really understand תוספות׳ס *Tosafot's* answer, but if you look
at תוספות *Tosafot*, אין שואלים בשלום אשה כלל *Ein Sho'alin Bishlom Ishah
Klal*, says והא דאמר בפרק הפועלים *Veha De'amar Beperek Hapo'alim*, איה שרה
אשתך *Ayeh Sarah Ishtecha*, ששואלים בשלום האשה על ידי בעלה *Shesho'alin Bishlom
Ha'ishah Al Yedei Ba'alah*, you can ask after the well-being of a
woman through her husband, the גמרא *Gemara* explicitly says from there you
see you can—of a wife, I should say. היינו דוקא בשאילת שלום
*Hainu Davka Bishe'ilat Shalom*, that's only in terms of שאילת שלום *She'ilat
Shalom*, אבל לשלוח לה בשלום אפילו על ידי בעלה אסור *Aval Lishlo'ach
Lah Bishalom Afilu Al Yedei Ba'alah Assur*. I have no idea what
that difference was. Okay, somebody can tell me what that means. But,
you know, but it is an interesting—you know, you're talking to a
friend, right? Are you not allowed to say, "Oh, please send my
best to your wife"? Is that, you know, where—what exactly is the—the
difference here? What?
Can inquire how she's doing
but can't send her good wishes?
I guess—hope you don't send her a message, right?
Oh, sending her a message. Oh, please send her my best. Is
that sending her a message? I guess so. So that would be
אסור *Assur*.
And—that you'll have a child.
Oh, right. Oh, oh, you mean that's okay to send a mess—but
they weren't telling her, "Tell her you'll have a child," they told
him, "You'll—you'll have a child."
They said your wife will have a child. All they said was,
איה שרה אשתך *Ayeh Sarah
Ishtecha*, and she's there, and
then maybe—maybe, I think—I think it's more like Jonathan was saying, that
תוספות *Tosafot* was maybe saying "How's your wife doing?" is okay, "Tell
your wife that I wish her well" is not okay, right? So—so
you're not allowed to say, when you're talking to—you know, a guy
talking to another guy, you're not allowed to say, "Oh, tell—send your
wife my best." Again, the question is also obviously how much does
this change the same way כל באשה ערוה *Kol Be'ishah Ervah* changes,
how much does this change based on our context?
Any other—occasion in other places in the גמרא *Gemara* that שמואל *Shmuel*
had these—took these positions?
Well, right, so the גמרא *Gemara* is going to actually get to
that in a minute, some position that just came up now, but
some of these are recorded also. כל באשה ערוה *Kol Be'ishah Ervah*
definitely is recorded elsewhere, משתמשים באשה *Mishtamshin Be'ishah* is in another גמרא
*Gemara* on פ״א ע״ב *Pei Aleph Amud Bet*. So I—I haven't tracked
all of them, but some of them definitely, if not all of
them, are elsewhere. Okay, but yes, that's a good—you're thinking ahead already.
Okay. Now שלחו
לה דביתהו, so now רב נחמן’s wife ילתא, who people might remember
was a pretty sharp, but also a pretty sharp cookie there, so
she sent to רב נחמן and she said to him,
שרי ליה
תיגריה, Shari lei tigrey, instead of get rid of, dismiss his case,
get rid of him already, דלא נשויך כשאר עמי הארץ, Delo nishvach
kishar amei ha’aretz, that he won’t make you like just a normal
עם הארץ, am ha’aretz, he’s showing you up left and right, could
you please just finish his case and get done with this. אמר
ליה, מאי שייתא דמר הכא, Mai shayata demar hacha, so רב נחמן
now had to try to
double back and protect himself, so he said, oh what brings you
here, רב יהודה, what makes you... so he says אמר ליה, תפקדתא
דמר שדר בתראי, Tifkadta demar shadar batrai, what brings me here? You
called me to a בית דין!
אמר ליה, השתא דשותא דמר לא גמירנא, Hashta deshuta demar lo gamirna,
so רב נחמן said, I don’t even understand, I can’t even talk
to you in a normal conversation, you’re such a higher level than
me, I can’t even understand your normal conversation, תפקדתא דמר משדרינא למר,
Tifkadta demar mashdrina lemar, do
you think I would send you a הזמנה hazmanah to בית דין?
חס ושלום, Chas veshalom, I would never do such a thing! So
אפיק תפקדתא דמר מבי חדיה, Afik tifkadta demar mibei chadeih, he came
with the writ, he took it out of his pouch, from his
breast, from his jacket, ואחזייה ליה, Ve’achzeia lei, and he showed it
to him, ואמר ליה, Ve’amar lei, הא גברא והא דיסתא, Ha gavra
veha dista, here I am, here’s the man, here’s the writ, don’t
claim you didn’t send this to me, you sent this to me,
you tried to show me that you were a greater authority than
me, and it’s clear obviously you had no right to do so.
אמר ליה, הואיל ואתא מר להכא, Ho’il ve’ata mar lehacha, fine, since
you’ve already come here, okay, לישתעי מילי, Lishtaei milei, let’s look at
the case, כי היכי דלא לימרו מחנפי רבנן אהדדי, Ki heichi delo
lemru machanfe rabbanan ahadadei, so people shouldn’t say that we flatter or
we show favor to one another, you’re here, probably he was admitting
implicitly I shouldn’t have called you, but now that you’re here we
have to at least pro forma go through this case. אמר ליה,
מאי טעמא שמתיה מר לההוא גברא, Mai ta’ama shamteih mar le’hahu gavra,
why did you put him in נידוי? nidui? So he says דציער
שליחא דרבנן, Ditzayer shlicha derabbanan, because he caused pain to
a messenger of the רבנן, he caused pain to my attendant and
he also defamed me. ונגדיה מר, Venagdeh mar, and why didn’t you
give him lashes? רב מנגיד על דמצער שליחא דרבנן, Rav mangid al
dematzayer shlicha derabbanan, רב would give lashes to somebody who would cause
pain to a representative of the רבנן. דאדיף מיניה עבדי ליה, De’adif
mineih avdi leh, it’s better to put him in נידוי nidui which
is more lasting and a more clear sort of censure than to
give him lashes. מאי טעמא אכריז מר דעבדה הוא, Mai ta’ama achriz
mar de’avda hu, and why do you say that he was a
slave? אמר ליה, דרגיל דקרי אינשי עבדי, Deragil dekari inshi avdei, because
he would call other people slaves as a regular thing.
ותני כל הפוסל פסול ואינו מדבר בשבחא לעולם, Vetani kol haposel pasul
ve’eino medaber beshbacha le’olam, finally getting back to this, anybody
who invalidates others himself is invalid. ואמר שמואל במומו פוסל, Ve’amar Shmuel
bemumo posel, it’s because he has the same problem in himself.
So let’s just read one more line and we’ll finish up tomorrow.
אימא דאמר שמואל, Eima de’amar Shmuel, when does שמואל say that it’s
his own problem? למיחש ליה, Lemichash leh, to mean that we should
be suspect that that guy has the same issue. לאכרוזי עליה מי
אמר, Le’achruzei aleih mi amar, that you should proclaim that he’s a
slave, take it as a matter of fact? Like isn’t that taking
it a little far? Again, this is a teaching of שמואל, רב
יהודה is constantly teaching the teachings of שמואל. So that is a
good question, like really you’re going to proclaim that he’s a slave?
And at the end of it is, I’ll just read אדהכי והכי,
Adehachi ve’hachi, while they were discussing, אמר ליה ההוא בר דינא לרב
יהודה, Amar leh hahu bar dina leRav Yehuda, so this person, the
litigant, came forward and he said to רב יהודה, לדידי קרית לי
עבדא, Ledidi karyat li avda, you had the חוצפה chutzpah to call
me a slave? דאתינא מבית חשמונאי מלכא, De’atina mibeit Chashmonai malka, I
descend from the חשמונאים! Chashmonaim! אמר ליה, הכי אמר שמואל, כל דאמר
מבית חשמונאי קאתינא עבדא הוא. Kol de’amar mibeit Chashmonai katina avda hu.
Oh, just proved my point, because שמואל says anybody who says they
came from the house of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim is a slave, because
that house of חשמונאים Chashmonaim was totally wiped out and it was
what's his name,
who was the guy who הורדוס, Hordos, right, who took over and
assumed the name of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim and הורדוס Hordos was a
slave. So thank you very much for proving my point, you’re a
slave, and we’ll continue tomorrow, but רב יהודה really showed
up רב נחמן.